foreign
last time we talked about
what you Sankara
and the intention behind speaking
and
a while ago madini actually said that um
in regards to the class
but there is this when one attends
the breath and the intention behind it
there is this discrepancy
between the intention to do so and the
body breathing and so should something
similar be
soft in regards to speech
yeah recognized yeah
well that's what I was saying last time
I think you can think and Ponder but
then the body will be speaking for you
but it's the assumption
through non-clarified extent of thinking and
non-clarified extent of thinking and
pondering the assumption is that your
thoughts spill through a map it's the
same thing it's the same direction but
it's not
and outlining that
the clearer it is the less able you
would be to
assume that body that speaks
on your behalf that creature this is
what this would refer to
you can't even be seen as as mine
anymore you just you're just there doing
these things having thought and pondered
speaks like this that's like this but in
order to um
see that see it's a discrepancy from the
point of view of assume directionality
of ownership
but if that discrepancy is cultivated
sufficiently enough you realize oh no
the ownership was the description part
these are just heaps
next to each other as they always have
been the body the Mind superimposed feelings
the body the Mind superimposed feelings
is just there in their own domains
um that's it though where he says oh
I've been so cheated by this mind I've
been assuming just porn just yeah yeah
it was just this and it was just this
and it was just this but in order to see
those domains
um
the Aggregates existing on their own
yeah that yeah it's not just uh it's not
just a view you can adopt on double
things um you have to have been withdrawn
um you have to have been withdrawn
from centrality thoroughly seeing the
Peril in it because any notion of
central pleasure requires that overlap
that directionality that discrepancy to
be assumed
so for as long as internally the mind is
has is not turned away from the value of
Pleasures through the senses you you're
not going to see the separate domains
because you're still connecting them
so to speak
that's even for like the um
the outlining of that thinking and
pondering the verbal thoughts you need
to
be secluded and you need to be away from
other people speaking
because the external speech that you're
hearing is already kind of fueling that
Assumption of the directionality that
your thoughts spill him out so you
wouldn't be able to outline it
if you're in a chapter of other people
because your thoughts are already on the
level of that external chat so you need
to be physically withdrawn from it
while in silence in that and so that you
can hear your own thoughts speaking
correctly independent of the
non-speaking map
and then cultivate the discernment of
that so
so
um are you talking about realizing that
the souls are not you
um no no no it's about
um
Discerning the difference between the
thoughts thinking and pondering the
extent of the images verbal thoughts
verbalizations and the actual physical
speech so basically so basically
yeah
perform it seems obvious to to see that
that verbalization is one thing internal
globalization and like actual speaking
is a different thing so but what is uh
yeah well it is obvious but the thing is
like um verbalization internally
um verbalization internally
is taking up your body externally
that is not obvious to people if it were
they would be free from sensuality
you are taking up your mouth through
your thoughts
you're placing your mind in your head
your point of view behind your eyes all
these overlaps are good Traders
and if you look behind your eyes you
won't find your mind if you dissect the
mouth you won't find your verbal
thinking there either
yet it's kind of there
and it's a way of gratuitous taking up
of a domain that cannot be taken up
so it's on the level of
the possibility of speech
and that is seen as the possibility to
to step outside
of thinking and pondering that's the
assumption that people don't are unable
to uh yeah yeah but uh
what is the
let's let's approach it differently
what's the Practical benefit of that
I've seen the Assumption seeing the
extent of your thinking and pondering
of your thinking and pondering
seeing the extent of your mind talking
and differentiating from body breaking
into speech
what's the what's the Practical benefit
of that type of composure responsibility
responsibility
in the sense of seeing
um
yeah I mean you find yourself in this in
this ignorance this assumption so you
find yourself oneself
already assuming assuming
um
the the
the possibility of speech being outside
okay so those assumptions yeah
uh are they result
of
I don't know
secrets and mistakes and hidden information that
and mistakes and hidden information that
you haven't figured out
or are the results of certain states of
mind that you're still cultivating and
engaging with and acting out of yeah the
latter exactly so then should this uh
practice of Discerning the extent of
your thinking and pondering in silence
in solitude
should that be about figuring out where
these assumptions are and undoing them
or should that be about not perpetuating
those mental states exactly yeah
so how'd you then not perpetuate those
mental States through the practice of
Discerning the extent of your thinking
pondering by seeing
by seeing
how our one is
um not currently
deciding the extent of one sinking and
wondering yeah that's the overall goal
that's the problem but is that your
mental state in the current so in your
connection in your current action is
your mental state mentally yes it is
yeah which one so I I mentally I'm
acting out of this assumption the the uh
well you can't help that though
so if you sell cash you're not act out
of this assumption that's rooted in
assumption but what I'm pointing at is
what we discussed last time is
the fuel for that assumption it's not
your assumption that it still hasn't
figured out where the line is is the
action well it's the desire and lust
yeah yeah that then obviously you act
out of and that starts with the mental
state so then your thinking and pondering you
so then your thinking and pondering you
will be acting I mean the the whole
skillful thought versus the unskillful
thought maintaining the skillful context
it's all form of acting but it's acting
that's that's sort of paired with
adjones you're not acting out of trying
to get rid of this no it's okay you are
acting in order to remove the fuel for
the mind that feeds these assumptions so
how do you do that that's what I'm
asking basically practically then how do
you use your verbal thinking how do you
use Discerning the extent of thinking
and pondering to stop providing fuel
it is kind of like an activity in itself
to see the non-activity to kind of um
yeah see but practically so so you're
thinking to yourself I mean
you're establishing the correct order
through thinking and pondering um so so
um
so okay we're back then on to it so
here's the problem because
um
there is no correct order
is that how the problem is being fueled
like literally can you appropriate can
you really own the five Aggregates no so
yeah even if you want to not you can't
really do much about it yeah yet you
keep forgetting and you keep getting
lost in the notion that you're the owner
what fuels that notion
since you cannot really pervert the
order of the Aggregates yet the
Assumption of perversion is there why
what fuels it
it's not not knowing because you know
now that order cannot be perverted yet
you're still doing it
every now and then why well you're doing
it all the time no I mean what are you
doing it all the time well yeah
every now and then it sounds
as if like no every now and then you add
fuel right sure you might have your
Notions all the time but every now and
then you add a fuel but not knowing how
you're adding the fuel that's how you
will keep adding the fuel so how do you
add the fuel to the wrong Notions of
ownership self and everything else by
acting out of craving the last diversion
last of it so surely those shouldn't be
the criteria
you want to be using
not not these kind of
borderline abstract Notions of yes as I
said you need to get the information but
if you keep revolving around information
about what comes first and will come
second you are just revolving around the
ideas while in practice
you are still inadvertently fueling the
fire yeah yeah so
yeah yeah so
let me ask you that even more blindly
what are the five ways you could be
fueling the fire of assumption
there's only five ways what are they
what are the five ways five witnesses
what are they start we're doing more
okay so this is sensuality sensuality
then as you'll do your will then there's
the donors 12000 kind of thing yeah the
restlessness removes anxiety yeah
and doubt exactly so those are not the
abstract things those are
state of mind their mind affected with
them the extent of your thinking and
pondering in silence away from
you know other people speaking and
noises in that sense
that's what you'd aim for okay what is
my current state of mind
is the sensuality present
can they sensuality arise if it's not
the reason
and you can have your mind talking about
it yeah to yourself
you don't need to verbalize it
physically but because
but because
mental verbalization thinking and
pondering to its full extent
is done presently in regard to presently
enduring States
and see that's like the um
the whole uh tendency to clarify
what the right view is you know what
comes first what the right order is what
the right assumption is yeah that's what
brought you here
but the point will come when you start
to recognize on now that is one of the
hindrances I'm acting out of pressure to get rid of
I'm acting out of pressure to get rid of
this non-clarity that I have clarified
thousands of times before
I suppose and thought about it and
clarified it and then I forgot about it
and then I clarified it again after I
thought about it so you realize okay so
how about now
I don't emphasize what I should be
thinking that I view is I start
emphasizing not having the five
hindrances present here and now for this
duration of time
and the only way to not have five
hindrances present is to fully clarify
them yeah
they won't happen magically like now I'm
in a state Hindus is a disappear no they
will disappear when you have fully
understood uh discerned endured okay so
is the centrality present yes there is
okay so then continue yourself internal
verbalized non-speaking questioning yeah
is this for my harm what does this
result into is this pressure towards
sense pleasure is it Pleasant or
unpleasant really
is it annoying or peaceful which one is
it
and practice that type of see you're now
establishing a different context in
regard to the presence of a mind
effective with centrality because the
usual context is mind effect of
potentiality context is get rid of this
get more pleasure content content
content yeah context is go for the
content well now context is going for
the content is never a good idea it was
always resulted in my harm hum for of
others loss of perspective and
everything else the swamp of everything
else that follows
what do you know nothing now think more
about the same swamp the same context
the same period and then you will see oh
look mind is now free from that same
Central desire that was here before
is the real world present
I don't know well bring up something
that used to annoy you they don't know
you yesterday they don't know you 10
years ago that Phil you will or anger
have the mind of anger present okay so
is this for my benefit
is this really beneficial like is this
really what I want even when I'm angry I
mean is this the outcome I want no I
want this to not be here in the first
place so when does it become a problem
yeah oh so I've been making it a problem
by trying to get rid of it or acting out
of it or taking it for granted reflect
on those on that new context and they
will will subside in the face of that
which you hate let's put it that way
same then with drowsiness is the lack of
energy the sleepiness is the laziness is
there unwillingness to make the effort
then again reflect question verbalize
the context in regard to that
so how much time do I have left I don't
know so really easy it's going to be end
of the world if I don't go to sleep
immediately or if I go and do this or do
this or if I just sit and continue
verbalizing these things and thinking
about them correctly and then the energy
will come back
and then same goes for worry
is there anything that would bother me
okay well see that's a problem if I'm
still subjected to worry means I'm not
this passionate towards the world
towards the senses why am I not
Disturbed this passionate talks about
the census why am I still subjected to
worry can it be just you know accidentally not
can it be just you know accidentally not
my own doing or am I still doing things
in regard to the world that are based on
a certain degree of
concern entertainment distraction either
way to some extent I'm still using the
world and the content it provides maybe
not the sensual and kind of hateful
aspects but other ways am I still
engaging with the world for the sake of
forgetting about myself
oh well that's why I'm still subjected
to worry
and then doubt
the last one so
is the doubt present in his mind no can
it wait well let's see do I doubt that
all of this practice I've been doing now
in regard to the four hindrances is that
right or wrong
no I'm pretty clear that it's right and
if anything's to be right he's closer to
okay so to this extent at least I'm free
from doubt so to this extent at least
now I am free from the five hindrances
so what is the context of that
there is a state of mind there is a
degree of pressure there is thinking of
pondering but there is also seclusion from
but there is also seclusion from
unwholesome States
there is also a certain degree of
impeccability there is feeling there is perception
there is feeling there is perception
there are obviously intentions
oh look I described the factors of the
first genre
which yes it says once you have been
thoroughly withdrawn from hindrances the
pleasure will be born from that
seclusion but you won't be withdrawn from it
but you won't be withdrawn from it
magically he won't be withdrawn from it
on account of meditation experience
you'll be drawn on account of diligence
that we said so many times before
so it's not even a hard work in a way
just okay yeah
keep the precepts don't engage with
centrality restrain your speech and when
you're secluded what do I do okay well
there you go what do I do well let me
see if the mind is free from centrality
free from meal will and rinse and repeat
and then you fall off
and you find yourself how'd you fall off
can you fall off accidentally can you
just trip over and oh look I'm back into
sensuality and ill will and so on
can that happen well
well
I suppose by not becoming
um established don't you you're not
established you couldn't get established you got
you couldn't get established you got
distracted whatever else
that still doesn't mean you fell off
how'd you fall off
can you fall off accidentally by acting
out by acting out so it cannot happen by
accident so even if you don't make any
effort as long as you don't make the
effort to fall off you won't fall off
either that's the point
so you can forget but not fall off
exactly yeah you can forget you cannot
be diligent enough
and and you know like you can be
careless in that regard but you're still
not falling off for as long as you don't
start going back to sensuality the
content the distraction of the world and
so on
and those things cannot be done
accidentally they're always on the level
of choice
and that's the whole point of this as I
said Discerning the extent of thinking
and pondering
the extent of
that um
vachi Sankara the verb of thinking
there's no problem about it at all
quite the opposite it's actually quite a
palpable anchor that you can use
to discern and sustain wholesome states
of Mind free from hindrances
that's the point of the practice is not
magically just just talking repeating
words to yourself because that's how you
enter somebody or something through a
mantra or through as I said before like
saying what you're doing while you're
doing it and no
I mean if you do any of that it would be
for the sake of revealing the state of
mind uh
uh
clarifying it if it's not clear
no let me stop and think about this
hey let me verbalize those thoughts so I
don't get sort of
um
distracted by my own thinking
and yeah for that you you can't have
people talking around you
and the clearer this becomes then when
you do speak
engaging in speech or physical actions
will not because they've been purified
beforehand is that magically says
is that magically says
then when you do engage it will not be
reintroducing that the Traders overlap
that you know it cannot happen
but one thing is to know it another
thing is to actually develop your mind
in regard to it
and that's also just brings you back to
another point I want to highlight so
as we said like so you can't you cannot
accidentally fall back
it's just impossible
so then universally speaking when people
do fall back
regardless of the views
regardless of the meditation practices
and techniques and what they think
meditation is or what meditation should
achieve
that is the reason why they fall back
it's not because they haven't done their
vipassana Retreat long enough or it's
happened because you know the the Mantra
was not powerful enough no it's because
they went and acted towards sensuality
there is no other cause for falling off
even if you spend rest of your life
you completely muddled ridiculous
mystical views
yeah you might not be getting to the
goal of the Buddhist practice but you
are not falling off
for as long as you're not going back to
sensuality as simple as that
as simple as that
and when people and see people fall off
because they chose to act against the
precepts against sense restraint
and while it's right there in the face
the reason for the falling off they
don't see they think oh it's because I
have not been on a long enough retreat
so next time and then next time they
commit even harder they make even more
effort into the area that makes no difference
into the area that makes no difference
they go and spend three months in a Cell
somebody brings the food and all their
watches their Sensations and so on and
that makes no difference that was not
the reason for the falling off
and it will be not their reason for
being picked up and they might pick up
the practice there again not because of
their meditation technique but because
they're withdrawn from sensuality but
they don't see that as the core Factor
they think that's all secondary which is
why when they go against it they also
think of that secondary doesn't matter
as much which is why they go against it
which is why they take precepts
conditionally
and even if somebody's practicing for
the sake of deities and whatnot
again therefore they will fall off from
therefore they will fall off from
whatever the practices or they will not
fall off from whatever the practice is
is if they act or potentiality or not
yeah yes hindrances and so on yeah but
predominantly sensuality really
lack of sense restraint and falling back
onto gratification of your senses that's
it
that's what I did say in that another
even if somebody even if a monk does not
develop any distinction at all remains
with confused mindfulness no right View
but he keeps the precepts and even for
the rest of his life he's just in tears
and pain of restraint but he still
remains keeping the presets he's heading
up not down so to speak
and that's important to emphasize
because you could still oh I've fallen
off because I haven't discerned the
principle with this this is sufficiently
enough no you might not have discerned
the principle sufficient enough so they
might not be the results of that
discernment but you haven't fallen off
you've fallen off if having not
discerned the principle with this this
is sufficient enough then you went and
acted towards sensuality that's why you
fell off
and that's that's not something you can
just oh how did this happen
because it's always on the level of
conscious choice
I might just like slightly backtrack to
what you were talking about
um
before in regards to
actively questioning oneself in regards
to the sensual thought that has arisen
or could arise for example
I mean you were saying it already but I
thought it might be good to highlight
the points that
um in this sorta that you've been
mentioning a lot like the two types of
thoughts um
um
when it starts by saying okay essential
thought has arisen in me now like I see
okay this is for my dangers for my harm
of others harmful Etc and then it
continues a non-sensual quote or a
rosemary or thought of pronunciation
um it's kind of natural I guess to think
like there's a sensual thought and then
there's a non-sensual thought that's
like a different thing or it's a
different type of object for example or
I'd have to think of but it's not quite
that like as in it's exactly the type of
thinking of seeing the problem or the
danger of the sensual thought that has
arisen that constitutes that's the
nonsense
like you can pick and choose between the
two exactly no it's on the level of the
state of mind that's like even if for
you to discern the central thought
correctly first you gotta see your mind
where it's affected by it or not because
what you think central thoughts are
to start with that's already the result
of your essential thoughts so first
physical seclusion
precepts physical seclusion guarding of
the sense doors as we said before losing
or overcoming the concern and joys in
regard to the entire world to any extent
to every extent
so then your own thinking and pondering
the domain the speech the creature there
can be outlined because it's not being
interfered with and then you get to see
what state of mind induced in regard to
it whether it's leaning towards it or
leaning away from it whether it's it's
inclining towards pleasure or not
whether and and that's how you start and
cultivating it first you have to take
that elephant out of that Wilderness of
its own sensuality
but for as long as the
there is a thread remaining a
possibility for an elephant to still
kind of re-engage every now and then
and you don't keep an eye on that well
to that extent it's going to remain wild
to that extent it will not except your
verbal thinking and directing into the
right context it will only take it
conditionally
and that's also the difference see
Once the mind
is now
purified from the hindrances
from the hindrances
with the sustained diligence effort
whenever you're alone you Ponder you
clarify you let it in the order if it's
oh it's not Central okay
what is the context of an on Central
mind how does it feel so to speak how
does it look okay I'm now in the state
of a non-central mind okay let me
remember that let me pick up the signs
and features of that so having developed
your mind like that
then all those things that you learned
before that you need to learn such as
with this this is and the Right View and
all of that
then falls into place without you
needing to force it there you start
recognizing it because the things they
were obscuring it have subsided
that's why even for the right view in
the sutas the mind is free from
hindrances at that time
usually thanks to the Buddha in the
suttas but obviously sometimes people
themselves made the effort
and that's why like that's why those
things are not seen on the level they
need to be seen because there are
obstructions there
but if for as long as a person just
keeps emphasizing seeing seeing and
seeing it ignoring what's obstructing
that very seeing they are so Keen to do
they won't see it they won't see it on
that right level
and that's the element of Faith here
okay but but I want yes I want to
understand it and through that wanting
of understanding I have learned that
there are things that are obstructing me
to understand it thus in order to
understand it let me then out of Faith
put this desire for understanding aside
and actually understand these hindrances
first and free my mind from them
yeah but what if all engines will doubt
right okay so now I shall understand
that not by providing answers but by
contemplating verbalizing the context in regard to the
verbalizing the context in regard to the
State of Mind effective with doubt
is this for my benefit how many times in
the past have I been affected by doubt
how many times in the past have I seek
three answers how many times in the past
I found the answers
did this ever stop no same like
centrality how many times you seek the
gratification scratch ditch just to find out now it is
scratch ditch just to find out now it is
even more pressuring oh well surely then
this principle of Doubt is the same
I engage in satisfying the content of
the doubt providing the answers so to
get rid of the pain of the doubt means
I'm now more under the thumb of the pain
next time it comes I'll be even more
pressured to act and is that for my
benefit no
so I shall then for as long as the mind
of Doubt is present also I will have
this context of danger peril
um harm present so then the mind will
turn away from the doubt
from wanting to act out of the doubt
and like you were saying earlier
you can also like test the mind like
what if I never
get the answer to this like can I handle
that yeah situation or like um yeah what
if well you need to be prepared to never
get the answer yeah that's the point
yeah because getting the answer rooted
in the intention of getting rid of the
pain means more pain yeah so it will
never be an answer
you can yeah like do that with all the
five five entrances just test yourself
like that thing that made me anxious or
angry yeah exactly can that can that
make me anxious and angry now like right
and or can anything else do so and if it
is so what do I do then what do I do
then oh yeah even more so now there is
mind affected with anxiety or fear what
do I do then
well there you go
that's the first question I asked myself
why do I need to do anything
what's the pressure what's the reason
for me wanting to do something about
this present state of mind I'm not
acting out of it I did not create it I
did not invite it yet it's here why do I
need to do anything about it
and if doing anything about it would
that constitute acting out of it would
it make it worse
oh yeah it would every single time it
did so then
I shall only remain contemplating the
danger in doing something about it
until the Mind calms down
and then if I do something about it
it'll be fine because it won't be rooted
in that pressure to do something about
it which is bothering me
and that's why you oh what do what do I
do what do I do why oh because it's
unpleasant so I want to do something
because I want to get rid of the pain
he's there for my benefit
how many times in the past I've
experienced that tried to get rid of a
pain through doing something
accepting paying at the face value and
acting out of it
and did that ever remove the liability
to pain
or do they just manage
the current pressure made me feel
alright but that made me more dependent
on doing something about it
so that's what you do
you don't act and sustain the context in
regard to it for as long as it's present
and the mind will have to turn away
because he never wanted it in the first place
I understand what I'm saying so he said
that this urbanization
this urbanization
is is uh well it's connected to the
first genre basically
um but
should this happen only when you um
when you uprooted the hindrance is at
least in the present situation or is
this uh engagement with with them with
the hindrances like working with them is
already the first genre I presume it's
not because they're still present
uh yeah I mean technically first John a
pleasure first John is after the mind is
now thoroughly abiding in that 92 margin
or too little
so you're not inclining towards the the
content of the hindrances nor are you
trying to get rid of it
so you have calmed down within it
um
but really that pleasure of Janna would
not have come if this engagement in the
work has not been completed and that is
that's what I said in the previous
uh well I don't know which one now but
one of the previous talks the um
the the closest to a method for Jana
it's that purifying your mind from the
hindrances because that's what every
pseudo Dimensions gradual training
that's what it describes
so keep the presets gotta sense those
moderate anything watchfulness of your
intentions and then dwelling in
seclusion and then
First Watch of night second world
tonight Third Watch of night and all
these diligence after pin the bird
before Pinder bud what he does is he
purifies his mind from the five
hindrances and just day in day out that's his work
and just day in day out that's his work
that's his diligence and then after that
his mind is now thoroughly secluded from
um
those five bases they would keep the
Mind engaged with on wholesome things so
now he's fully withdrawn from it and
then the pleasure born from that
seclusion comes to be
so he's like yeah that's the genre part
but you realize that pleasure is really
just the result that pleasure of safety
is the result of the work of making
yourself safe in regard to these five
hindrances five imperfections of mine five weakness
five imperfections of mine five weakness
of wisdom all these descriptions of it
that's the work that's the method that's
the technique but
good luck doing it mechanically
and the thinking and pondering as a the
jhana factor is it like
is whatever mind thinks about in this
state without hindrances Well yeah if
you made the effort thoroughly and that
might take
a long time to to overcome the five
hindrances to to learn how to uh compose your mind
to to learn how to uh compose your mind
away from them from these five kind of
sticky aspects they would drag you back
into centrality or will and so on then
whatever the mind were to think you
won't think those five things you won't
think things within them and that's what
bodhisatta realize himself oh wait now
having been withdrawn from the
hindrances through maintaining the right
context he recognized oh hold on I
haven't had those thoughts anymore why
don't I just now let this mind roam
around I don't need to keep constantly
policing it and sustaining it with the
right context and that's where he
started calming down internally
even further because he said first he
was just the two types of thought he was
just thinking wholesome
establishing the context of wholesome
thoughts in regard to the unwholesome
hindrances and then he said tireless
energy arrowsing me day in Day Out
he was just uninterrupted energy
but that in in and of itself it's not as
nice as a complete piece it's still
nicer than sensuality
tireless energy effort Zeal just
effortless when it's an energy is
tireless it feels effortless
but it's not as peaceful so then hiroku
knows okay so why don't I stop this now
because he was done for the purpose of
overcoming the five hindrances and now
the mind is not even like even when I
let go of it it's not going into the
hindrances so why don't I let go of it
and that was the simile of like first
it's regathering your cows heard from
eating in other people's pastures and
then these crops that they used to be so
inviting are now two distant too far
removed taken away so there is nothing
enticing these cows you can't let them
roam you don't need to keep them time
down and hitting them with a stick and
so on because they're not wandering
anyway and then you can even have a
little snooze under the tree you know
they will not go anywhere and then the
confidence is born from that seclusion
even further
but you know exactly how it came to be
it wasn't just magically I just fell
asleep and look cows didn't go wow
that's amazing now you know why they
didn't go because you prevented any any
reason for their going way beforehand
and way thoroughly
so that's the that's the work aspect
and so basically then you're saying that
in the in this
so two kinds of thoughts when he was
saying that that well I see that there
is a the total not in Northern real
non-sociality in this at this point he
was already abiding in the first in
China for well now I mean the outlining
the moment to know the point is
uh if you're withdrawn from the 5000
cents if your mind is on its own without
your input without your context not
thinking sensuality not not going to a
deal will not going towards laziness no
then that's that's all you need to be
concerned about like focus on that
really then when Jana starts from what
moment onwards I wouldn't worry about
that um that would be the result of of this
um that would be the result of of this
which needs to be done
but if you worry where it starts or if
you still think it's important to know
where exactly that pleasure of seclusion
starts means your seclusion will be
conditional for that pleasure
but any pleasure that you want before
you were secluded will be a central
pleasure will be underlined by craving and thus
will be underlined by craving and thus
it will not be the pleasure of seclusion
so you really need to stop
emphasizing or even or just regarded as
equally dangerous
because it would be the pleasure that
you want and the pleasure of Jannah is
not something you can want
it's not underlined by Lust underlied by
lust craving and that's why it's a
wholesome pleasure
because wanting pleasure it's a
hindrance it's the first hindrance
and people can like even if it's not
unusual in the world for people to
restrain themselves give up lots of
things for the sake of a greater
pleasure later on oh let me you know
um save things not
um go to the bar not go to my usual
Pleasures so that I can go on this great
holiday and yeah get a reward yeah
delayed gratification delayed
gratification and that is that's still
within the hindrance that's still
meditating with the hindrances
as they would have said so many times so
nobody would say that those that that
way of acting like restraining myself in
such and such ways so that I can get a
holiday later on is not sensual it's
very obvious that it's essential yeah
but it is kind of the same principle if
somebody does these
um things for the sake of the pleasure
of Jannah so and that's really that's
the criteria that's the criteria I think
even like the you know the the later on
student commentaries of the sutras even
they kind of figured it out through all
the texts that oh yeah if you want Janna
you need to stop wanting it there there
can be no craving or desire for pleasure
present um because that's still within the
um because that's still within the
hindrance and because of that it won't
be the genre
so same if you see if you have a desire
towards that John a pleasure pleasure
meditation there you go verbalize your
thinking in regard to that for next two
weeks until it's absolutely clear why do
you want to do it what do you expect
from it
was the problem with not having it
where's the issue
you know it seems to me that there is a
difference between craving for Jannah
and and Desiring vagina it's probably
the same as uh Desiring Enlightenment so
you cannot say that I don't care
completely if I if I become a knight or
not uh
but well overall sure you you want to be
enlightened but what matters is how you
go about it yeah yeah that's that's the
thing so I think this is different
between desire and craving or whatever
no no it's still a design
like that's why like again if somebody
is not relinquishing that desire they
won't go beyond the desire
yes that desire is what made you keep
the precepts majorly read the suitors
but if you are still meditating out of
that desire well you're bound with the
hindrances as simple as that
yeah so the difference you're presenting it's
so the difference you're presenting it's
not that linear it's yeah I want to be
free from suffering which is why I
started in the suitors reason that
rooted desire yes but it's the desire
they can eventually make me understand
the desire and give up all desire
altogether so are you giving up desire all together
so are you giving up desire all together
or are you trying to justify a certain
type of desire in the face of another
type of Desire
so basically you're saying that that
so giving up hindrances all the means
giving up even desire to be enlightened
well yeah because the desire to be
enlightened that you know of is the
desire of sensuality
if it weren't you would already be
enlightened without
acting out of the hindrances it's like
that this distinction well yeah it
seemed like people can't give up the The
Virtue and Duty Factor yeah oh boy I
give that up means I give up
Enlightenment well so to speak to some
extent but you don't give it up because
you already learned what you need to do
correctly
so yeah you should have desire for Jana
and then learn what
how to go about it correctly and if you
again depending on what instructions you
read but if you read the suit as you
realize oh it's about overcoming the
hindrances so first hindrance is desire for
so first hindrance is desire for
pleasure
so am I doing these practices to get the
pleasure well I'm hindered by craving
for pleasure
is there for my benefit is that for
benefit of others what am I trying to
achieve with it and so on and so forth
and then you will give up the desire for
pleasure and then you'll get the
pleasure of Jonah because you gave it
all up
but not before you give it all up
if you think you can have it both ways
that's meditating with hindrances
so another thing I was thinking about in
regard to this similar like
topic is that it's not necessarily that
that
trivial or obvious
to say what constitutes
the practice of purifying your mind from
hindrances because somebody might say oh
I do this this and this and that works
really well for me like I I see that I'm
kind of well anything can become a
mechanical mindless method yeah but if
if you emphasize what needs to be
emphasized which is a preset guarding of
the sense doors
inclusion watching your intentions
you won't be able to to to uh make it
mindless and mechanical for too long
in other words the tendency will be
there but if you don't compromise of these
but if you don't compromise of these
underlying development principles of the
gradual training it will even itself out
but it's when everything else is taken
conditionally and then such reviews will
then be enough oh yeah no this is what
helps me this is what I can do sometimes
like this sometimes like that and thus
look I'm free from hindrances
but then you if you're honest you need
to look at the entirety of your life and
see if that is the case
ask yourself okay like okay I feel
dispassionate let's say in regard to
things that I used to be passionate
about but
but
why like on what base is this and is
this dependent on me continuing to do
something else for example that has kind
of replaced this pleasure that I used to
have and just check like am I am I
liable to worry anxiety to fear to pain
in the future
um you know like you might confuse it
you're free from it now because there's
nothing bothering you but as I said just
to reinvoke something that could bother
you and see if you bought it and if you
bought it well does your work
yeah and it's not about again it's it's
always has to be priorities like this
state of mind instead of like you can
say oh I used to be very concerned about
this thing and now I'm not concerned
about that anymore but it's not and also
in the world it says purifying your mind
from unwholesome things does not mean
preventing these things from arising
means basically uh
developing imperative ability in regard
to them so not being moved by
unwholesome things arising that's how
they will stop arising
and that's not something you can do
mindlessly because
things they move you are on the level of
your mind
so that's the only place you can see
them state to mind
they would stop arising because you
've stopped acting in a way that's
adding fuel for long enough yeah the
wild dogs will stop coming could you
stop providing food stop leaving the
food in front of the gate and they'll
stop coming
yeah they will carry on coming
for a while
expecting the food but if you simply
never put the food out again never
fueled the fire anymore it will stop you
yeah
yeah and it was funny like yeah if you
if you understand this principle then
you would kind of stop being worried
about when will the dog stop coming
exactly when there will never be any
dogs yeah yeah because that was another
problem yeah the problem is that my
actions were resulting directly in those
dogs being here harassing me
actions routine greater version
distraction hindrances